DAN KLEIN: So let's think about
adversarial games and how we're going
to formalize this idea of a search
problem, where you're not the only
person acting in the environment.
There are a lot of different
kinds of games.
So, in particular, the kinds of
techniques we're going to talk about
today are going to apply to a very
specific class of games.
You'll notice when I did an overview
of game technology, I was talking
about a very narrow class of games.
I didn't talk about poker.
That's a game of imperfect
information.
We're not going to talk
about that today.
I didn't talk about things like Star
Craft, which is another example of
imperfect information.
I didn't talk about anything
stochastic.
Poker also has a stochastic
element to it.
And I didn't talk about cases where
there are multiple players beyond two.
So what are we going to
talk about today?
Well, it's going to be zero-sum games,
and they're going to be deterministic
games, and they're going to be
games of perfect information.
What we want is we want an algorithm,
which allows us to calculate a
strategy which tells us what
to do in each state.
Now think about how this is
different from Search.
In Search, I gave you the search
problem, and what you gave me back was
a plan or a path.
It was a sequence of actions
that executed and it was
guaranteed to succeed.
That's not going to work here, because
we don't control our opponent.
So we can't just give a plan that's
guaranteed to succeed.
What we need to do is we need to give a
function which tells us in any given
say what to do.
That's this policy.
In the game case, it's often
called a strategy.
So we can formalize games.
If we wanted to formalize this, we
could do it in multiple ways.
There's less consensus on exactly what
the formalization is and what notation
to use, but you would have a set of
states just like in a search case.
Now there are multiple players and they
typically take turns in the way
we formalize these games.
There's a set of actions and
maybe different players
have different actions.
And then the analogy to a successor
function is something we can call a
transition function, though today
we're actually going to continue
calling a successor function, because
it won't be ambiguous today.
And what this does is this tells us how
the state evolves in response to
the various actions.
There's a terminal test which tells
us when the game is over.
So it's kind of like the goal past
fr a search, and now there
are terminal utilities.
This tells us for an end state,
how much of this is worth
to each of the players.
OK.
The solution to a game like this is a
policy which maps states to actions.
As I said before, we're going to be
interested in zero-sum games.
You've probably heard that term.
What does that mean?
In a zero-sum game, like what's
shown on the left, we do
have adversarial agents.
So in this case, we're going to imagine
we have two agents, except
they have opposite utilities.
So when we think about a terminal
state, if one likes it,
the other hates it.
Because they have opposite values on the
outcomes, we don't have to think
about the blue players utility
and the red players utility.
There's just one function, except the
blue player wants to maximize it and
the red player wants to minimize it
And this is a really nice thing that
we can think about there being a
single function.
Because this lets us reason about the
extreme case of pure competition and
adversarial search.
But what about in general.
In general, this won't be true.
In general, when you have multiple
agents acting, you don't imagine that
they're purely adversarial.
They simply have their own utility
functions which sometimes align and
sometimes don't.
So, for example, if you imagine
you have these two agents.
And they're picking out their own colors
from the gem file, well, they
both be happy.
And in fact, one making progress
actually helps the other by getting
rid of some of the things
it doesn't care about.
So the case of a general game, the
agents are going to have utilities
that are going to be independent.
They can both like an outcome.
They come both hate the outcome.
Or they could also have opposite
preferences just like
the zero-sum case.
Because of this general flexibility,
you can have cooperation.
You could have indifference, and you
could have competition, between the
agents, and also subtle combinations
of these things.
All of these things are possible
in the general case.
And in fact, will fall out of
computational reasoning
in the general case.
We're going to talk about non-zero-sum
games later.
Today we're going to talk
about pure competition.
So there's one function.
One agent maximizes it.
The other minimizes.